<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matt Catrett</title>
    <description>Matt Catrett</description>
    <link>http://www.mattcatrett.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.mattcatrett.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>On Reading</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If books were roads, some would be made for driving quickly - details are scant, and what details there are appear drab - but the velocity and torque of the narrative is exhilarating. Some books, if seen as roads, would be make for walking - the trajectory of the road mattering far less than the vistas these roads might afford. The best book for me: I drive through it quickly but am forced to stop on occasion, to pull over and marvel.”
― Peter Mendelsund, What We See When We Read&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not set many goals for this new year, but I have decided to continue a habit that I developed over the last year: voracious reading. A few years back, I read Edmund Morris&amp;#39; &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.com/03757567870&quot;&gt;The Rise of Theodore Roosevelt&lt;/a&gt; and one of the most memorable takeaways I had was how Roosevelt would read two or three books &lt;em&gt;each day&lt;/em&gt;. Can you imagine reading nearly a thousand books a year, while acting as President of the United States?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that tidbit in the back of my mind, my reading throughput has increased over the years. But since last May, after moving and discovering &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/22064165-matt&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt; I have been on a bender and I don&amp;rsquo;t plan on stopping. Officially, my goal is to read at least forty books this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have a few general guidelines (which I do bend from time to time):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read at a comfortable rate.&lt;/strong&gt; I can throttle up my reading speed, but I find that my short-term comprehension and long-term retaining of information decreases at a higher rate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two-to-one non-fiction to fiction ratio.&lt;/strong&gt; I enjoy good fiction, but I also love learning, so I tend to find this ratio to be my natural tendancy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to read multiple books at one time.&lt;/strong&gt; However, I tend to read fiction by itself so I can focus on the world that the author has created.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid to stop reading a book (or skim it if it is non-fiction).&lt;/strong&gt; Reading is supposed to be fun: keep it that way and don&amp;rsquo;t fret over quitting. I rarely have done this since I tend to research what books to read, which helps. But I have grabbed interesting-looking titles from the library only to lose steam midway through.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write about what you&amp;rsquo;ve read.&lt;/strong&gt; This is something I wish I started doing a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time ago. With the Kindle (and its apps) you can easily highlight passages and then view them without opening the book again, which is quite nice. However, writing down a few observations or quotes makes a great difference in how you retain the important stuff from your reading. I doubt I will remember every detail that I found interesting, but if I record a few into Evernote or a pen-and-paper notebook, I will be able to look back on them years down the road and re-trigger that memory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one rule that trumps any other: have fun. Sometimes I am in the mood to study a topic I am reading about; other times I just want to be taken on an adventure. Reading does not have to be a chore and you don&amp;rsquo;t need to collect read books like Pokémon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my &lt;a href=&quot;/books&quot;&gt;list of 2015 books read&lt;/a&gt;, thus far.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2015 19:19:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.mattcatrett.com/books/2015/02/03/on-reading/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.mattcatrett.com/books/2015/02/03/on-reading/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
